Pearson mss. II, 1896-1940 LMC 1822
Lilly Library
Pearson mss. II
1896-1940
Lilly Library
Pearson, Edmund Lester, 1880-1937
LMC 1822
1 Box 1 standard
2 bound
The Pearson mss. II, 1896, 1922-1940, consist of the correspondence and papers of Edmund Lester Pearson, 1880-1937, librarian.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
The Pearson mss. II, 1896-1940 contains letters and writings by librarian Edmund Lester Pearson (1880-1937). Born in Massachusetts, Pearson studied at Harvard College and then New York State Library School. Subsequently, Pearson worked as a librarian at the Washington D.C. Public Library and the Library of Congress. In 1908, Pearson became acting librarian of the Military Information Division in the War Department. And he became known, between 1906 and 1920, for his weekly column "The Librarian" that appeared in the Boston Evening Transcript. After 1909, Pearson also wrote a series of books and columns throughout his career: most notably, Theodore Roosevelt (1920) and Studies in Murder (1924), as well as his work on the Lizzie Borden murder case.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Writings, and Miscellaneous.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondents include Marie Adelaide (Belloc) Lowndes, 1868-1947, novelist, and William Roughead, 1870-1952, criminologist. A letter dated April 4, 1896, of Lizzie Andrew Borden, 1860-1927, alleged murderess, and a photograph of Miss Borden is included with the collection.
Note on Indexing Term - "Women": There is much correspondence with Marie (Belloc) Lowndes, 1868-1947, writer of mystery stories based on actual crimes.
Related Material
See Pearson mss. and Pearson mss. III, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1981
Women; Trials (murder); Women murderers; Pearson, Edmund Lester, 1880-1937
- Correspondence
  - Borden, Lizzie. To Mr. Childs, 4 April 1896 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Accompanied by portrait of Borden
  - 1922-1936 (Box 1)
  - Lowndes, Marie (Belloc) - Pearson, 1923-1940 (Box 1)
  - Lowndes, Marie (Belloc) - Pearson, undated (Box 1)
  - Roughead, William - Pearson, 1922-1928 (Box 1)
  - Roughead, William - Pearson, 1929-1937 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books in Black or Red manuscript and printed (Box 1)
  - First Aid for Puzzle Fans printed (Box 1)
  - Dime Novels printed (Box 1)
  - Murder at Smutty Nose manuscript, photographs and printed (Box 1)
  - Studies in Murder manuscript and printed (Box 1)
  - Theodore Roosevelt printed (Box 1)
  - Studies in Murder 1924 edition (Box 2)
    Includes notes from Pearson on the book's publishing history as well as pasted-in articles and ephemera, including a dried flower and a note relating to Murder at Smutty Nose
  - Murder at Smutty Nose 1926 edition (Box 2)
    Includes notes from Pearson on the book's publishing history as well as pasted-in articles and ephemera
- Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Printed (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Diary of Pearson, E. L., 13 January 1923-3 March 1935 (Box 1)